Guide to the Salmagundi Club Photograph Collection 1898-1943 PR 182
New-York Historical Society
Salmagundi Club Photograph Collection
1898-1943
New-York Historical Society
Salmagundi Club
PR 182
6.68 Linear feet (4 boxes)
The Salmagundi Club Photograph Collection contains photographs of dinners held by the club between 1898 and 1943, including dinners sponsored by Samuel T. Shaw and the club's annual "Get Together Dinner".
Provenance
Twenty-five of the photographs were the gift of the Estate of Samuel T. Shaw, November 7, 1946; other additions were made to form the collection.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Historical Note
The Salmagundi Club was formed as the New York Sketch Club in 1871 by a group of artists and art patrons; it changed its name in tribute to the 19th century book of tales and miscellany published by Washington Irving. The club held its meetings and events in rented rooms at 14 West 12th Street from 1895 until 1917, when the club purchased its own brownstone at 47 Fifth Avenue.
Samuel T. Shaw (1861-1945) was the proprietor of the Grant Union Hotel, which was located on the southeast corner of 42nd Street and Park Avenue, across from Grand Central Terminal, from 1874 until 1914. An art collector and patron of living artists, Shaw hung the hotel walls with his personal collection of works by American painters. He was closely associated with the Salmagundi Club, the Society of American Artists, and the National Academy of Design, and awarded cash prizes for the best picture at the annual exhibitions held by those institutions.
Shaw gave the "Shaw Prize" at the Salmagundi Club exhibits for fifty years, and would sponsor an annual dinner party of the artists in competition for that year's award. A commercial photographer was engaged to make a panoramic group portrait of the jovial and formally dressed painters at their dinner table. At the center of each photograph appear two easily identifiable men: the award-winning artist from the previous year (bedecked with a laurel head wreath), and their great patron, the bearded, white-haired (and usually unjacketed) Samuel T. Shaw, often sitting beneath the Club's portrait of Shaw by Wayman Adams.
Scope and Content Note
The Salmagundi Club Photograph Collection contains photographs of dinners held at the club between 1898 and 1943. There is also one satirical illustrated diploma issued to Samuel T. Shaw in 1899. The collection is divided into five series that reflect the decades covered by the material; thereunder the photographs are arranged chronologically. Many of the dinners represented were those sponsored by Samuel T. Shaw, but the collection also includes other Club group meals, such as their "Get Together Dinner" held each fall, which celebrated the return of the artists to New York from their summer painting colonies at the mountains and seashores.
Commercial photographers in the collection include New York firms George W. Lawrence Company; Cawood, Inc.; Krohn & Kollatz; Schlesinger Studio; Standard Flashlight Company, Inc.; and Century Flashlight Photographers, Inc.
Arrangement
Photographs have been arranged into five series based on date:
Missing Title
Series I: Turn of the Century
Series II: The Teens
Series III: The Twenties
Series IV: The Thirties
Series V: The Forties
Related Material at the New-York Historical Society
The Society's Library also holds the Samuel T. Shaw papers (BV Shaw, Samuel T) which include records kept by Shaw in his capacity as treasurer of the Salmagundi Club's Artists Fund.
Photographic prints.; Group portraits.; New York (N.Y.); Art patrons.; Artists.; Dinners and dining -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Clubs -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Art -- New York (State) -- New York -- Societies, etc. -- Photographs.; Krohn & Kollatz; Schlesinger Studio; Shaw, Samuel T., 1861-1945.; Standard Flashlight Company, Inc.; Cawood, Inc.; Century Flashlight Photographers, Inc.
- Series I: Turn of the Century
  Scope and Contents note
  The materials are arranged chronologically. Multiple copies of photographs, when present, are indicated by numbers in parentheses.
  - Tile Party, 1898 Jan 14 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Satirical diploma issued to Samuel T. Shaw (watercolor), 1899 May 7 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1A)
  - Charles Hawthorne dinner (5), 1905 Mar. 15 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Harry Vincent dinner, 1908 Jan. 29 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Frank Russell Green dinner, 1909 Feb. 24 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: The Teens
  The photographs are arranged chronologically. Multiple copies of photographs, when present, are indicated by numbers in parentheses.
  - Gifford Beal dinner (2), 1910 Feb. 24 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  - F. Luis Mora dinner, 1911 Feb. 22 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  - William J. Aylward dinner (3), 1912 Mar. 13 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
  - W. Granville Smith dinner (6), 1914 Mar. 12 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  - Howard Giles dinner (3), 1916 Mar. 9 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Daniel Garber dinner (5), 1917 Mar. 8 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bruce Crane dinner, 1918 Mar. 7 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
- Series III: The Twenties
  - Fiftieth Anniversary Dinner, 1921 Oct. 31 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
  - Edmund W. Greacen dinner (3), 1922 Mar. 2 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
  - Get Together Dinner, 1922 Oct. 27 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
  - George P. Ennis dinner, 1923 Mar. 1 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
  - Frank Tenney Johnson dinner, 1924 Mar. 6 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
  - John E. Costigan dinner (3), 1925 Feb. 12 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
  - Roy Brown dinner, 1926 Feb. 11 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
  - Chauncey F. Ryder dinner, 1927 Feb. 10 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
  - Twenty-fifth Anniversary Dinner of the Samuel T. Shaw Purchase Prize, 1929 Mar. 7 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
- Series IV: The Thirties
  - Charles S. Chapman dinner, 1930 Mar. 6 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12)
  - George M. Bruestle dinner (8), 1931 Mar. 5 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13)
  - Ernest L. Blumenschein dinner, 1932 Mar. 3 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 14)
  - Eugene Higgins dinner (2), 1933 Mar. 2 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 14)
  - Gordan Grant dinner, 1935 Mar. 7 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 15)
  - Royal Cortissoz dinner, 1937 Mar. 19 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 15)
  - Get Together Dinner, 1937 Nov. 12 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 15)
- Series V: The Forties
  - Hobart Nichols dinner (2), 1940 Feb. 8 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 16)
  - Wayman Adams dinner, 1941 Feb. 6 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 16)
  - Carl J. Nordell dinner, 1942 Feb. 12 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 16)
  - Harrison Cady dinner (3), 1943 Feb. 11 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 16)